Guide to the Gail and Stephen Rudin collection of Civil War letters, 1861-1865.
Rudin, Gail and Stephen collection of Civil War letters
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Gail and Stephen Rudin collection of Civil War letters, 1861-1865.
4696
Stephen, Rudin
.8 cubic ft.
Correspondence
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Civil War era letters
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The Gail and Stephen Rudin collection of Civil War letters contains letters from Dr. William Harrison Githens: twenty-three letters to his wife, Sarah P. Robbins, one letter to his daughter Louise, two letters to an unnamed daughter, and one letter to his granddaughter Sarah. Dr. Githens mentions studying medicine in Philadelphia, various battles and the conditions for the soldiers, descriptions of battle wounds, church services, concerns about his family and other matters relating to "this cruel war" from Hamburg and Chattanooga, Tenn.; Philadelphia, Penn.; and near Rossville, near Marietta, near the Chattahoochee River, near Atlanta, in Atlanta, Ga.; Holly Springs, N.C.; Washington, D.C.; and Hamilton and Carthage, Ill. There is also an obituary of Dr. Githens from the Carthage [Illinois] Republican, July 13, 1904. Also included are 119 letters and other pieces from Civil War soldiers, officers, a wife in a camp, a musician in a band, a chaplain, a nurse, and at least one civilian to relatives, wives, friends, officers, pastor, and sweethearts re preparations for war, homesickness, battles, President Lincoln reviewing the troops, executions, and the surrender of General Lee. The writers of these letters were from much of the United States: Alabama; Arkansas; Washington, D.C.; Delaware; Georgia; Illinois; Kentucky; Louisiana; Maryland; Mississippi; Missouri; New York; North Carolina; Ohio; Tennessee; Texas; and Virginia.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Rudin, Stephen,; Githens, Sarah P. Robbins.; Lee, Robert E.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865.
Subjects:
Medicine--Study and teaching--United States.
Places:
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Casualties.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Medical care.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Letters from various authors
Boxes 1-3
Series II. Letters from Dr. William Harrison Githens
Box 4
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Letters from various authors
  - Writer: C.F. Noething Writer's location: Belleville, IL Writer's Military Unit: Unknown Addressee: Brother, 4/17/1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Discusses Sexual Prowess (with three other family letters - no date, 8/31/61, 4/12/62).
    Number of pages: 4 and envelope.
  - Writer: Walter Writer's location: Nashville, TN Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, Unknown Addressee: Father, 4/20/1861 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    A week after Ft Sumter, the South prepares for war.
    Number of pages: 2
  - Writer: Unsigned Writer's location: Pinckneyville, IL Writer's Military Unit: Union, Unknown Addressee: Sister, 5/11/1861 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Passionate patriotic letter - "Never no Never" (Partial letter).
    Number of pages: 4
  - Writer: Charles Ritner (Musician in Band) Writer's location: Washington Arsenal Grounds Writer's Military Unit: Union, Pennsylvania Volunteers Addressee: (Blank), 6/15/1861 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Document - Discharge for severe homesickness.
    Number of pages: 1
  - Writer: Elmora Anthony Writer's location: Camp Trousdale, TN Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, 7th Tennessee Infantry Addressee: Mother, 6/17/1861 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Wife has chosen to live with husband in camp.
    Number of pages: 5
  - Writer: Pvt. John G. Darling Writer's location: Washington, DC Writer's Military Unit: Union, 2nd New Hampshire Volunteers Addressee: Friend Dwight, 6/27/1861 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Describes Washington D.C. and speaks of his negro beauty.
    Number of pages: 4. Illustrated.
  - Writer: Wells C. Haynes Writer's location: Fairfax Court House, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 2nd New Hampshire Infantry Addressee: Wife, 7/17/1861 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Letter written on captured colorized bookplate.
    Number of pages: 2. Illustrated.
  - Writer: Thomas M.C. Hane Writer's location: Washington, DC Writer's Military Unit: Union, Company C 6th Regiment Addressee: Friend Dick, 7/25/1861 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Regarding battle of "First Bull Run" plus error printed envelope.
    Number of pages: 4 and envelope. Illustrated.
  - Writer: Chaplain Levi W. Norton Writer's location: Camp Caldwell, DE Writer's Military Unit: Union, 72 New York Infantry Addressee: Wife, 8/26/1861 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Chaplain's letter describes services with sketch of tents and map.
  - Writer: Charley Writer's location: Camp Union Writer's Military Unit: Union, 1st Massachusetts Cavalry Addressee: Wife, 9/8/1861 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    "I go forth without fear of trembling"
    Number of pages: 3
  - Writer: Cadmus M. Amoss Writer's location: Camp Washington, Yorktown, VA Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, Cobbs Georgia Legion Addressee: Wife, 10/1/1861 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Witnesses his first storm at sea - War has set him and thousands of others, ten years behind in business.
  - Writer: A.A. Abernathy Writer's location: Bowling Green, KY Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, Unknown Addressee: Grandmother, 10/16/1861 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    "It is not my desire to kill any man"
  - Writer: Francis W. Baker Writer's location: Falls Church, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, Unknown Addressee: Wife, 10/22/1861 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    "Killed on their own soil by their own countrymen"
  - Writer: Pvt. Thomas Williams Writer's location: HQ 1st Regiment Writer's Military Unit: Union, 1st Regiment, New York Cavalry Addressee: Col. McReynolds, 11/19/1861 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Re: Charges against an officer for violent conduct.
  - Writer: Charles H. Mendell Writer's location: Annapolis, MD Writer's Military Unit: Union, 23rd Regiment, Massachusetts Volunteers Addressee: My Kind Pastor, 11/21/1861 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    One of the hardest temptations is a game of cards.
  - Writer: "C.C.N." Writer's location: Camp Benton, St. Louis, MO Writer's Military Unit: Union, Unknown Addressee: Wife, 12/1/1861 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Describes life in the barracks - Makeshift Thanksgiving feast (Lithographed letterhead)
  - Writer: "A.K." Writer's location: Camp Barker, Cairo, IL Writer's Military Unit: Union, Unknown Addressee: Cousin Hattie, 12/8/1861 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Describes scouting in Missouri - "Battles are not fought without the loss of life and some must fall"
    Number of pages: 8
  - Writer: Capt. William B. Alexander Writer's location: Camp Andrew Writer's Military Unit: Union, 23rd Massachusetts Infantry Addressee: Wife, 12/27/1861 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Officer and slave talk sex.
  - Writer: 3rd Lt. William Nunnally Writer's location: Camp Ruffin, VA Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, 13th NC Infantry Addressee: Brother, 12/29/1861 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Mentions baseball, visit to CSS Merrimack, getting drunk on eggnog, kite flying.
  - Writer: Mifflin Gilbert Writer's location: Camp Goodman Writer's Military Unit: Union, 28th PA. Infantry Volunteers Addressee: Sister, 2/9/1862 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Hide bottle of brandy in loaf of bread"
    Number of pages: 2 1/2. Illustrated.
  - Writer: E. Henry Writer's location: Camp Sorthumberland? Writer's Military Unit: Union, 96th PA Infantry Addressee: Father & Sisters, 2/23/1862 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Balloon Reconnaissance over Manassas (See also Balloon 2/27/63 and 6/18/63).
  - Writer: Pvt. George R. Baldwin Writer's location: Fort Scott, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, Co. C - 1st Connecticut, Heavy Artillery Addressee: Friend Ellery, 3/29/1862 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Whore House Escapades.
  - Writer: J. W. Austin Writer's location: New Madrid, MO Writer's Military Unit: Union, 5th Iowa Infantry Addressee: Brother, Sister, Father, 4/4/1862 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Damaging storm, cannonating at Island #10, soldiers being killed and injured playing with shells.
  - Writer: E.S. Reed Writer's location: City, NC Writer's Military Unit: Union, 23rd Massachusetts Regiment Addressee: Friend, 4/5/1862 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Fighting in knee deep mud. "I got struck twice with a ball"
  - Writer: Hank Lamereaux Writer's location: New Bern, NC Writer's Military Unit: Union, Unknown Addressee: Brother, 5/16/1862 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Soldier struck by lightning.
  - Writer: Capt. John N.Wiedemyer Writer's location: Camp Churchill Clark, Corinth, MS Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, 6th Missouri Infantry Addressee: Wife, 5/16/1862 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    "Give one a patriot's grave but not a coward's name"
  - Writer: Unsigned Writer's location: Camp No. 7, near Corinth, MS Writer's Military Unit: Union, Unknown Addressee: Wife, 5/25/1862 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Soldiers prick their ears only when bulldogs (cannons) bark. Regiment issued new clothing.
  - Writer: Capt. John M. Huntington Writer's location: Clarksburg, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 86th Regiment Ohio Volunteers Addressee: (Blank), 7/9/1862 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Whimsical Civil War Broadside
  - Writer: Pvt. Isaac Newton Writer's location: Ft Morgan, N&C RR, TN Writer's Military Unit: Union, 37th Illinois Infantry Addressee: Sister, 7/12/1862 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Soldiers falling in love with locals - Trading salt and coffee for whiskey with rebels - deer hunt - (Original drawing on masthead) (See also Trading 6/25/63, 7/20/63, 8/10/64, 12/18/64).
  - Writer: Col. J. A. Mulligan Writer's location: Camp Comiskey, New Creek, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 23rd Illinois Volunteers Addressee: Major Naughton, 8/2/1862 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    "It is sad to think that through all this quiet and magnificence ... there shall be blows and blood and ruin"
  - Writer: Daniel Davis Writer's location: Near Culpepper C.H., VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 46th Pennsylvania Volunteers Addressee: Brother, 8/3/1862 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Re: Counterfeit Confederate Notes
  - Writer: Major Clark S. Edwards Writer's location: HQ, Harrison Landing, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 5th Maine Infantry Addressee: Wife, 8/5/1862 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Midnight artillary battle - "Had a merry drunk"
    Number of pages: 5 and envelope.
  - Writer: C.S. Graham Writer's location: Heyworth Writer's Military Unit: Union, Unknown Addressee: Brother, 8/18/1862 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Town buys a flag for its soldiers going off to war.
    Number of pages: 1 1/2
  - Writer: Rebecca Wiswell Writer's location: Georgetown Seminary Hospital Writer's Military Unit: Union, Nurse Addressee: Friend, 9/20/1862 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Union nurse writes of a soldier's death after Antietam (See also Nurse 9/29/63).
  - Writer: Pvt. Edward J. Rinebold Writer's location: VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 141st Pennsylvania Volunteers Addressee: Friend, 9/26/1862 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Soldier shoots himself in foot to try to get a discharge.
  - Writer: E.T. Austin (sister of soldier) Writer's location: Unknown Writer's Military Unit: N/A, Civilian Addressee: Zadak Austin, 5th Battalion, NY Infantry, 10/15/1862 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    How the brave soldier was wounded at Antietam.
  - Writer: Pvt. Luther F. Davis Writer's location: Near Perryville, KY Writer's Military Unit: Union, Ohio 121st Infantry Addressee: Brother, 10/28/1862 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Describes "camp houses" and drilling
    Number of pages: 3 and envelope. Illustrated.
  - Writer: Samuel F. Emerson Writer's location: Near Leesberg, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 3rd Maine Infantry Addressee: Father, 10/30/1862 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    "I have already fought on seven different battlefields and I have seen enough"
  - Writer: J.J. Campbell Writer's location: Brooke's Station, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 42nd Pennsylvania Regiment Addressee: Friend, 11/23/1862 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Describes foraging for food in a pig pen.
  - Writer: C.R.P. Rogers Writer's location: Port Royal Writer's Military Unit: Union, U.S.S. Wabash Addressee: Son, 12/20/1862 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Father writes a moral code for his son.
  - Writer: Pvt. Joseph H. Capen Writer's location: Camp Stevenson, Newbern Writer's Military Unit: Union, 44th Massachusetts Infantry Addressee: Parents and Brother, 12/21/62-1/5/63 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Lengthy description of all types of camp daily activities.
    Number of pages: 20 and envelope.
  - Writer: Sgt. Lewis Sims Writer's location: Fort Pickeren near Memphis Writer's Military Unit: Union, 89th Indiana Infantry Addressee: Wife, 12/23/1862 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    In a state of alarm, waiting to do battle with the rebels - mentions he is teaching a slave boy to read and write.
  - Writer: Pvt. Albert C. Pray Writer's location: Fort Schuyler, NY Writer's Military Unit: Union, 20th Maine Infantry Addressee: Brothers and Sister, 1/7/1863 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Comments on the war and on politicians and generals - Discusses forced march, Battle of South Mountain.
    Number of pages: 10 and envelope.
  - Writer: Capt. Chief Quartermaster Charles G. Sawtelle Writer's location: Stafford Heights, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 2nd Corps. Army of Potomac Addressee: My dear Aurell, 1/14/1863 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Officer apologizes for getting drunk (Name signed in artwork).
  - Writer: J.C. Williams Writer's location: Unknown Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, 7th South Carolina Addressee: Parents, 2/1/1863 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Snowball fight (See also Snowball 2/27/63).
  - Writer: Lewis Writer's location: Near Murfreesboro, TN Writer's Military Unit: Union, 3rd Brigade 3rd Division 20th Army Corps Addressee: Hettie, 2/4/1863 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Describes a tour of the picket lines and the devastation around them - Plus slave story.
  - Writer: William S. Campbell Writer's location: Near Fredericksburg, VA Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, 5th Alabama Infantry Addressee: Bill, 2/27/1863 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Snowball fight. Yankee balloons - "Fight them to the last".
    Number of pages: 6
  - Writer: Capt. Watson Sloan Writer's location: Headquarters Picket Post No. 4 Clarksville, TN Writer's Military Unit: Union, 102nd Regiment Ohio Addressee: Friends at Home, 3/5/1863 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Acts as a steamboat guard - using black labor for construction - a false alarm calls the regiment out to battle.
    Number of pages: 8 and envelope.
  - Writer: "M" (a woman) Writer's location: New Orleans, LA Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, Unknown Addressee: Friend, 3/21/1863 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Battle of the Parasols.
    Number of pages: 14
  - Writer: Capt. John M. Weidemeyer Writer's location: Camp at Grand Gulf Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, 6th Missouri Infantry Addressee: Wife, 3/27/1863 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Love Letter.
  - Writer: Sgt. J.E. Wallis Writer's location: Galveston, TX Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, 20th Texas Regiment Addressee: Wife, 4/7/1863 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Battle of Big Brothel.
    Number of pages: 2 and envelope.
  - Writer: Brother George Writer's location: Camp near Stafford C.H. VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 11th Corps Addressee: Sister, 4/11/1863 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Lincoln reviews the troops - "He looks haggard and careworn".
  - Writer: Pvt. Nathan Hallock Writer's location: Near Falmouth, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 124th New York Infantry Addressee: Father, 4/11/1863 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    "The President looks very careworn" - Review of corps by Pres. Lincoln and Gen. Hooker
  - Writer: Dennis Tuttle Writer's location: Camp Donna, Isabella, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, Unknown Addressee: Wife, 4/13/1863 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    A union corporal gives birth on the picket line.
    Number of pages: 4 1/2
  - Writer: S.C. Wilkerson (?) Writer's location: Allisona, TN Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, 18th Alabama Regiment Addressee: Wife, 5/7/1863 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    A loving letter.
  - Writer: Lt. Martin Miller Writer's location: McNairy Station, TN Writer's Military Unit: Union, Unknown Addressee: Sister, 5/21/1863 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Crossing Great Bear Creek - Ladies chew and smoke tobacco and have very large feet!
    Number of pages: 3 1/4
  - Writer: Corporal Roland J. Cook Writer's location: Bell Buckle, TN Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, 2nd Arkansas Infantry Addressee: Cousin, 5/25/1863 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Discusses Negroes being carried off and conscripted by the Federals.
  - Writer: H.R. Doud Writer's location: Camp at Banks Ford Writer's Military Unit: Union, Unknown Addressee: Friend, 6/18/1863 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    "The rebs throwed shells at our balloon but did not hit it".
  - Writer: David M. Cushing Writer's location: Near Port Hudson Writer's Military Unit: Union, 53rd Massachusetts Infantry Addressee: Brother, 6/25/1863 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Yanks and rebels sing - Flag of truce.
  - Writer: "Benby" Writer's location: Port Hudson Writer's Military Unit: Union, Unknown Addressee: Brother & Sister, 7/14/1863 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Fort Hudson surrenders-Rebels might have held on if they had not faced starvation.
  - Civil War Draft Notice, 7/14/1863 (Box 2, Folder 17A)
    Draft notice sent to a resident of Salem, Massachusetts informing him that he is "legally drafted in the service of the United States". Rudin # M-62A
  - Writer: Pvt. John Black Writer's location: Sharpsburg Ford, Potomac River Writer's Military Unit: Union, 12 Penn. Cavalry Addressee: My loving Friend, 7/20/1863 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Union chats with Confederates and gives them whiskey after Battle of Gettysburg.
  - General Orders No. 273, 8/7/1863 (Box 2, Folder 18A)
    Court martial of six soldiers who deserted and were sentenced to be shot. However, a compassionate Lincoln remitted all these sentences. Rudin # M-76B
  - Writer: Herbert Writer's location: Union City, TN Writer's Military Unit: Union, Unknown Addressee: Mother, 8/23/1863 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Excellent commentary on slavery and its ramifications.
  - Writer: Sgt. Sampson J.D. Whiteman Writer's location: Newbern, NC Writer's Military Unit: Union, 3rd New York Cavalry Addressee: Cousin, 9/13/1863 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    All male cotillion- Advice on associating with friends.
  - Writer: Edward Henry Writer's location: New Baltimore, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 96th Pennsylvania Infantry Addressee: Sister, 9/14/1863 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Drummed out of the Regiment.
  - Writer: Dr. Fossard Writer's location: Near Culpepper C.H., VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 146th Regiment New York Volunteers Addressee: Dan (?), 9/25/1863 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Union surgeon and his lady of easy virtue.
  - Writer: Phebe J. Parker Writer's location: Washington, DC Writer's Military Unit: Union, Nurse Addressee: Brother, 9/29/1863 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Civil War Nurse discusses nursing activities, touring Washington and seeing Pres. Lincoln (See also Nurse 9/20/62).
  - Writer: Capt. A.W. Alvord Writer's location: Camp Austin, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 109th New York Volunteers Addressee: Adjutant Jewett, 10/24/1863 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Pleading for Whiskey-with response by Jewett on verso.
  - Writer: James W. Bartlett Writer's location: Blain's Cross Roads, TN Writer's Military Unit: Union, 35th Massachusetts Infantry Addressee: Wife, 12/25/1863 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    First use of barbed wire-soldiers wearing all kinds of clothing, including women's.
  - Writer: Qtrmaster J.F. Andrews Writer's location: Washington, DC Writer's Military Unit: Union, 1st Rhode Island Cavalry Addressee: Wife, 1/3/1864 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Lincoln's New Year's Reception.
    Number of pages: 4 and illustrated envelope. Illustrated.
  - Writer: Pvt. Lewis Josselyn Writer's location: Baton Rouge, LA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 38th Massachusetts Infantry Addressee: Mother, 1/10/1864 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Going to a "nigger ball"
  - Writer: Corp. Arthur M. Stone Writer's location: Cumberland, MD Writer's Military Unit: Union, 34th Massachusetts Infantry Addressee: Mother, 2/4/1864 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Drunk soldier claims he was captured by the Confederates
  - Writer: Col. Charles W. Drew Writer's location: Port Hudson Writer's Military Unit: Union, 4th Infantry Corps d'Afrique Addressee: Col. Charles Dwight, 3/10/1864 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Hanky Panky in the Corps d'Afrique
    Number of pages: 6 1/4 and envelope.
  - Writer: Pvt. Benjamin M. Florence Writer's location: Unknown Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, 17th Virginia Infantry Addressee: Miss Ellen, 3/18/1864 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Love letter home.
  - Writer: A.A. Winn Writer's location: Madison Station, VA Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, Unknown Addressee: Father, 3/25/1864 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Fighting sham battle-Plus second brief undated letter.
  - Writer: Capt. Charles R. Taylor Writer's location: Grove Church, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 2nd Pennsylvania Cavalry Addressee: Col. Taylor, 5/2/1864 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Pertaining to woman coming into lines with information on CSA troops in the area.
  - Writer: Peleg Bradford Writer's location: Fort Sumner, MD Writer's Military Unit: Union, 1st Maine Artillary Addressee: Dearest Friend, 5/12/1864 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Love letter to "Cynth" McPherson (See also Love Letters 3/27/63, 5/7/63, 3/18/64, 7/2/64, 7/27/64, 10/26/64, 10/27/64).
  - Writer: Pvt. John M. Lovejoy Writer's location: Near Spotsylvania Court House, VA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 121st New York Infantry Addressee: Mother, 5/17/1864 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Battle of Spotsylvania - " a ball came so near to my head that I was knocked down by the concussion of air"
  - Writer: Pvt. Henry Webb Writer's location: Point Lookout Prison, MD Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, 50th Virginia Infantry Addressee: Mrs. Smiley, 5/26/1864, 6/10/1864 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Two remarkable letters written to the mother of a soldier Webb killed at the Battle of the Wilderness - Written on pages taken from a book.
  - Writer: Lewis Hanback Writer's location: Camp on Good Hope Battlefield Writer's Military Unit: Union, 27th Illinois Infantry Addressee: Darling Hettie, 6/1/1864 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Confederate soldier jumps into Yankee rifle pits - "How are you Yanks?"
    Number of pages: 3 and envelope.
  - Writer: Major Thomas Norris Writer's location: In the field near Dallas, GA Writer's Military Unit: Union, 111th Ohio Volunteers Addressee: Mother (Rebecca Norris), 6/6/1864 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    Recounts the horrors of war and the tragic death of his brother (James Norris).
  - Writer: Capt. Frederick B. Doten Writer's location: Hdqtrs Third Brigade Writer's Military Unit: Union, 14th Connecticut Infantry Addressee: Darling Georgie, 7/2/1864 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    First two pages love letters to Georgie Welles. Picket firing ceases by mutual consent so that both sides can cook their cakes and coffee.
  - Writer: C.C. Mobley Writer's location: Division Hospital near Petersburg Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, 43rd Alabama Infantry Addressee: Wife, 7/5/1864 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Written on Union Morning Report Form - Prepared to meet death and God - Mails delayed - Paid 50 cents for this sheet of paper and much more.
  - Writer: Thomas Jefferson Campbell (C ) Writer's location: Near Berryville, VA Writer's Military Unit: Confederate, 48th Virginia Infantry Addressee: Cousin, 7/19/1864 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Written on captured Union song sheet - has marched over 500 miles - unit has barely enough men for a color guard.
    Number of pages: 2 and envelope. Illustrated.
  - Writer: Unknown Soldier - Job Writer's location: Triana, AL Writer's Military Unit: Unknown Addressee: Flora, 7/27/1864 (Box 2, Folder 41)